<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://abrar2652.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://abrar2652.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-18T03:13:37+00:00</updated><id>https://abrar2652.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Md Abrar Jahin is a CS PhD student and Graduate Fellow at USC Viterbi. Abrar is affiliated as an AI Researcher and Multidisciplinary Scientist at the Center on Knowledge Graphs, Information Sciences Institute (ISI). His research interests lie at the confluence of efficient deep learning, quantum machine learning, geometric deep learning, and trustworthy AI, with applications in high-energy physics, healthcare, and supply chain optimization. His prior work spans reinforcement learning (RL), sentiment analysis, operations research, and comparative genomics. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">My SOP and PS for CS PhD @ USC</title><link href="https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2025/phd-sop-ps/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My SOP and PS for CS PhD @ USC"/><published>2025-04-08T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-08T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2025/phd-sop-ps</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2025/phd-sop-ps/"><![CDATA[<p>My SOP and PS have been approved and published on the cs-sop website maintained by MIT CSAIL PhD students. You can check for my contributions there. For Fall’25, only 6 incoming CS PhD students, including me, have shared their statements till today’s date (8 April 2025). Hopefully, they will be of your help.</p> <p><strong>PS:</strong> I am the first-ever and only KUET alumnus to get into USC CS PhD (Top 20 in AI) despite coming straight from a non-CS background.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="a-bit-of-background">A Bit of Background</h2> <p>I wrote the full SOP within a week in November. It was reviewed during a 1.5-hour Zoom session by Jeong Hee Kim (MIT postdoc), who told me my CV was better than many MIT grads she had seen; her feedback gave me a major confidence boost.</p> <p>I also received feedback from Alex Gu (MIT CS PhD student), Junaid Ali (PhD student, Purdue ME), and two of my KUETian senior brothers (Saadman Adip Huda and Dr. Khaled Mohammad Saifuddin) in the US. They all agreed my SOP was dense and needed trimming. But with 24 publications at the time, I found it difficult to leave anything out. For plagiarism checks, I collaborated with a Turnitin provider from my connection (University of Dhaka), who offered repeated checks at a minimal cost. My SOP had 0% AI-generated content and 0% plagiarism.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="my-published-sop-and-ps">My Published SOP and PS</h2> <p><strong>SOP and PS of Md Abrar Jahin (how I cracked the top schools considering the brutal funding conditions and in a competitive domain like CS-AI/ML Systems in Fall’25, despite coming from a non-CS background):</strong></p> <p>You can read the live Notion version here:<br/> 👉 <a href="https://cs-sop.notion.site/Md-Abrar-Jahin-1cc8b1bdf3c48045b424f7f61eff9321" target="_blank">View on cs-sop.notion.site</a></p> <p>Or scroll below to view the embedded PDFs:</p> <h3>Statement of Purpose (SOP)</h3> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/blogs/MAJ_SOP_USC.pdf" width="100%" height="800px" style="border: none; border-radius: 8px;"></iframe> <h3>Personal Statement (PS)</h3> <iframe src="/assets/pdf/blogs/PS_USC.pdf" width="100%" height="800px" style="border: none; border-radius: 8px;"></iframe> <hr/> <p><strong>My Visa Interview Experience (where I consolidated most of the information):</strong><br/> <a href="https://www.facebook.com/share/p/19Q2Jk9SC4/" target="_blank">https://www.facebook.com/share/p/19Q2Jk9SC4/</a></p> <p>✅ Follow my latest start-up, 3AI, targetting the MS/PhD aspirants in the USA: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/share/1F3zPkZLs8/" target="_blank">https://www.facebook.com/share/1F3zPkZLs8/</a></p> <hr/> <p><strong>References</strong></p> <p>[1] <a href="https://csrankings.org/" target="_blank">https://csrankings.org/</a><br/> [2] <a href="https://www.usnews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-science-schools/computer-science-rankings" target="_blank">https://www.usnews.com/best-graduate-schools/top-science-schools/computer-science-rankings</a></p> <hr/> <p>#abrar2652xhsa (my other HSA-related posts can be found following this hashtag)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhDApplication"/><category term="StatementofPurpose"/><category term="PersonalStatement"/><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My Statement of Purpose and Personal Statement for CS PhD Application in Fall 2025]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://abrar2652.github.io/assets/img/md_abrar_jahin.png"/><media:content medium="image" url="https://abrar2652.github.io/assets/img/md_abrar_jahin.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Childhood Academic Life</title><link href="https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2024/childhood-academic-life/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Childhood Academic Life"/><published>2024-07-15T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-15T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2024/childhood-academic-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2024/childhood-academic-life/"><![CDATA[<p>My educational journey has been profoundly influenced by my experiences at <a href="https://mcc.army.mil.bd/" target="_blank">Mirzapur Cadet College</a> and <a href="http://bograzillaschool.edu.bd/" target="_blank">Bogra Zilla School (BZS)</a>. These institutions have played a pivotal role in shaping my character and academic success. Through these formative years, I acquired essential qualities such as perseverance, stepping out of my comfort zone, taking responsibilities, and the determination to overcome challenges. I also learned the value of selfless friendship, leadership, and the importance of following a chain of command. Moreover, I developed skills in extempore speech, time management, decision-making, and task prioritization.</p> <p>My academic achievements were recognized through Government Board Scholarships in PSC (2006), JSC (2013), SSC (2016), and HSC (2018) exams. Notably, I secured the 17th position in the Rajshahi Board in the PSC exams.</p> <p>During my time at BZS for primary education, I excelled in a highly competitive academic setting, consistently achieving top ranks in annual academic assessments. I actively participated in various quiz competitions, securing victories in three competitions organized by renowned entities such as the United Nations and Kishore Kantho. Additionally, I organized a quiz competition on a rolling basis, engaging students in subjects like primary-level Olympiad maths, English, and general knowledge (both national and international categories). This initiative not only kept students involved but also generated revenue, with each set of quiz questions priced at 2 Taka and a grand prize of a video game DVD (FIFA 2010), resulting in approximately 500 Tk in revenue during 2010-2011. These experiences have significantly influenced my academic journey, fostering a deep-seated passion for continuous learning and personal growth.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="childhood"/><category term="life"/><category term="childhood"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My Childhood Education and Academic Achievements]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://abrar2652.github.io/assets/img/md_abrar_jahin.png"/><media:content medium="image" url="https://abrar2652.github.io/assets/img/md_abrar_jahin.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/></entry><entry><title type="html">Academic Career Perspectives</title><link href="https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2024/academic-career-perspectives/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Academic Career Perspectives"/><published>2024-05-11T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-11T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2024/academic-career-perspectives</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://abrar2652.github.io/blog/2024/academic-career-perspectives/"><![CDATA[<p>I firmly believe that being a researcher is not just a career but a way of life that demands perseverance, intellectual curiosity, and commitment to advancing knowledge. Under the supervision of Professor Jonathan Miller at OIST, I had the privilege of conducting PhD-level computational research while balancing the demands of my undergraduate studies. During this time, I observed the pressures of the publish-or-perish culture in academia but remained committed to conducting meaningful and ethical research. Under his guidance, I gained invaluable insights into how groundbreaking science is conducted, no matter how long the process might take. Professor Miller’s mentorship profoundly shaped my research approach, and being part of his lab was a transformative moment when his colleague, <strong><a href="https://www.oist.jp/research/svante-paabo" target="_blank">Professor Svante Pääbo</a></strong>, won the <strong>Nobel Prize in Physiology/Medicine</strong> (2022). The research I was pursuing at that time closely aligned with Professor Pääbo’s work, reinforcing my confidence in the potential impact of my efforts and elevating my aspirations to new heights.</p> <p>My experiences in academic research over past couple of years since 2021 has strengthened my belief that academia is the place where I belong. I am fascinated by the ethics, honesty and rigor that academia represents. Compared to the outcomes which are more apparent in industry, academia forces researchers to face these uncertainties and solve problems with much more harder questions over much longer timescales. Overcoming smaller technical challenges (which are still not easy) in academia has given me the greatest satisfaction and inspired me to pursue academic research. I am eager to join in a highly competitive environment and push myself out of my comfort zone, because I am peer-pressure-driven and consider this as a motivation.</p> <p>My philosophy of success is simple: I seek out individuals smarter than myself, collaborate with them, and learn from their expertise. My leadership experiences have taught me that while I cannot excel in every domain, I can bring brilliant minds together to achieve impactful solutions for the greater good of science and humanity. Throughout my academic journey, I have combined technical expertise, research experience, and interpersonal skills to accomplish ambitious goals that often seemed beyond reach.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="ethics"/><category term="academia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My Personal Perspectives about Life in Academia]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://abrar2652.github.io/assets/img/md_abrar_jahin.png"/><media:content medium="image" url="https://abrar2652.github.io/assets/img/md_abrar_jahin.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"/></entry></feed>